# Thomas Nok Hin Cheng

#### Curriculum Vitae

Email: nok.cheng18@imperial.ac.uk/ nhcheng@mit.edu > Phone: +44 (0)79 4055 6145 (UK)

Web: nhcheng.mit.edu & Google Scholar & Linkedin & ORCID: 0000-0001-7663-4120

#### **OBJECTIVE**

Raised in Hong Kong, my primary research interest lies at the interface of biomedical science and chemical engineering in which my main goal for a career in research is to develop new technologies to understand disease pathogenesis, such as the mechanistic understandings of Inflammatory Bowel Diseases, and the translation of discoveries to targeted therapies.

## **EDUCATION**

# Massachusetts Institute of Technology

September 2020 - Present

MIT-Imperial Exchange Student with concentration in Chemical Engineering, Biological Engineering

GPA: 5.0 (Junior Fall)

- · Selected as one of the five undergraduates at Imperial College London to participate in MIT-Imperial Exchange program.
- Relevant Coursework: 6.UAR Seminar in Undergrad Research (SuperUROP); 20.430 Fields, Forces, Flows in Biological Systems; 20.465 Engineering the Immune System in Cancer and Beyond; HST.176 Cellular and Molecular Immunology; HST.S43 Evolution of an Epidemic; HST.439 Viruses, Pandemics, and Immunity; HST.539 Interdisciplinary Science in Human Health and Disease

# Imperial College London

October 2018 - Present

Candidate for Masters in Engineering (MEng) in Chemical Engineering

Class Rank: 1/142 (Freshman)

· Awards: Institution of Chemical Engineers Books Prize; Procter and Gamble Prize

1/133 (Sophomore)

· Relevant Coursework: Biochemistry; Biochemical Engineering; Advanced Bioprocess Engineering; Modelling of Biological Systems

# HHCKLA Buddist Ma Kam Chan Memorial English Secondary School

September 2011 - June 2017

Hong Kong Diploma of Secondary Education

- · 5\*\* (Highest achievable) in Mathematics, Extended Mathematics, Chemistry and Physics.
- $\cdot$  A gap year from Autumn 2017 to 2018 upon graduation to recover from recurring long-standing illness.

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Shalek Lab - MIT, Broad Institute, Ragon Institute

September 2020 - Present

Undergraduate Research and Innovation Scholar at the Institute for Medical Engineering & Science (IMES)

- · Led the effort to develop compressed drug screening technologies on biological ligands and the modelling of ligand pools.
- · Project description: https://superurop.mit.edu/scholars/thomas-cheng/

# Dr. Rongjun Chen's Group, Imperial College London

November 2019 - Present

Undergraduate Research Assistant at the Centre for Advanced Therapeutics

- · Studied, prepared and characterized drug encapsulation with erythrocytes derived vesicles.
- · Initiated and directed computational studies on pH responsive bio-polymer PLP-NDA resulting in a manuscript in preparation.
- · Co-supervised five Chemical Engineering undergraduates on the interactions between cell membrane and variants of PLP-NDA.

#### Professor Jerry Heng's Group - Imperial College London

June 2019 - June 2020

Undergraduate Research Assistant at the Institute for Molecular Science and Engineering (IMSE)

- · Computationally verified and investigated solvent-dependent polymorphism of anti-epileptic drug Carbamazepine. [3]
- · Investigated the effect of nanoparticles in inducing Lysozyme crystallization for bio-separation using UV-Vis spectroscopy. [1][2]

## TEACHING AND PEDAGOGICAL EXPERIENCE

## Chemical Engineering Wiki - Imperial College London

January 2020 - Present

Co-founder/Student Partner

· Co-initiated and maintained a student-led wiki to help Chemical Engineering undergraduates with student-created notes.<sup>[5]</sup>

· More information: https://nhcheng.mit.edu/blog/imperial-chemical-engineering-wiki

# Social Determinants of Health and Systemic Racism in Healthcare - MIT Splash 2020

November 2020

· Co-taught a class to over 30 motivated high school students to raise awareness on global health equity.

# Undergraduate Teaching Laboratory - Imperial College London

June 2020 - August 2020

Undergraduate Research Opportunity Programme (UROP) Participant

· Developed teaching materials for remote teaching during the COVID-19 pandemic, including a partial differential equations course and laboratory modules enabled with augmented reality.<sup>[4]</sup>

# Imperial College Union - Imperial College London

October 2019 - June 2020

Chemical Engineering Year Two Academic Representative

· Introduced academic-focused initiatives including a question forum for cohort and answered over 1,000+ questions and held tutoring sessions for peers in academic need, during semester and the COVID-19 pandemic.

#### Pimlico Connection Tutor - Imperial College London

October 2019 - March 2020

· Taught STEM subjects at local secondary school weekly to improve the academic knowledge, confidence and interest of underprivileged pupils, whilst giving them an insight into university life.

## **AWARDS**

Procter and Gamble Prize (2020): Awarded to the top student of the year in 2<sup>nd</sup> Year Chemical Engineering

Second Year Dean's List (2020): Ranking in the top 10 % in the year for 2<sup>nd</sup> Year Chemical Engineering

Institution of Chemical Engineers Books Prize (2019): Awarded to the top student of the year in 1<sup>st</sup> Year Chemical Engineering

First Year Dean's List (2019): Ranking in the top 10 % in the year for 1<sup>st</sup> Year Chemical Engineering

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 1. Inguva P, Bhute VJ, Cheng TNH, Walker PJ, Introducing Students to Solving Partial Differential Equations in Python, Educ. Chem. Eng. (2021), doi: 10.1016/j.ece.2021.01.011
- 2. Chen W, Cheng TNH, Li X, Khaw LF, Yang H, Ouyang J, Heng JYY, Protein purification with nanoparticle-enhanced crystallisation. Sep. Purif. Technol. (2021), doi: 10.1016/j.seppur.2020.117384
- 3. Chen W, Karde V, Cheng TNH, Ramli SS, Heng JYY, Surface hydrophobicity: effect of alkyl chain length, coverage density and network homogeneity. Front. Chem. Sci. Eng. (2020), doi: 10.1007/s11705-020-2003-0
- 4. Rosbottom I, Cheng TNH, Heng JYY, A Computational Analysis of the Solid-State and Solvation Properties of Carbamazepine in Relation to its Polymorphism. Chem. Eng. Technol. (2020), doi: 10.1002/ceat.202000056

#### CONFERENCES

5. Walker PJ\*, Cheng TNH\*, Maraj M, The use and value of a student-led Wiki towards facilitating peer collaboration in Chemical Engineering. (2021) In Advanced HE 2021 STEM Conference.

# SKILLS AND INTERESTS

Skills: Laboratory (Flow Cytometry, Cell Culture, Confocal microscopy), Computer Coding (MATLAB, Python, R, Julia), Research Software (ASPEN, gPROMS, GAMS), Language (English, Cantonese, Mandarin, Japanese)

Research Interest: Organoid, Systems Biology, Microbiome, Immunology, Drug Delivery, Statistical Physics, Biophysics, Nanomedicine Activities: Public Awareness and Social Service Society, Chemical Engineering Society, Japanese Society, MIT Global Health Alliance, MIT Microbiome Club

### REFERENCE

v
Professor in Particle Technology
Dept. of Chemical Engineering
Imperial College London
E-mail: jerry.heng@imperial.ac.uk

Professor Jerry Heng

# Dr. Rongjun Chen Reader in Biomaterials Engineering Dept. of Chemical Engineering Imperial College London E-mail: rongjun.chen@imperial.ac.uk

# Professor Alex Shalek Associate Professor IMES, Chemistry, Koch Institute Massachusetts Institute of Technology E-mail: shalek@mit.edu

# Dr. Camille Petit Reader in Materials Engineering Dept. of Chemical Engineering Imperial College London E-mail: camille.petit@imperial.ac.uk